{"tossups": [{"question": "This politician dubbed the Smedley Butler-alleged \"Business Plot\" a \"Cocktail Putsch.\" This man's first act in office was to order the arrest of gangster \"Lucky\" Luciano, just before this man instituted a ban on the sale of artichokes. This collaborator of Robert Moses curbed the strength of Tammany Hall and was the first Italian-American to serve as mayor of a major city. A Queens airport is named for, for ten points which New York City mayor during the 1930s and '40s?", "answer": "Fiorello <b><u>La Guardia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country was governed by flight lieutenant Jerry Rawlings following a 1981 coup against the Convention People's Party. This country became the first colony in sub-Saharan Africa to achieve sovereignty under the regime of Kwame Nkrumah [[KWAH-meh en-KROO-muh]]. The only Black Secretary General of the United Nations, Kofi Annan [[KOH-fee ah-NAHN]], was originally from this country. The Ashanti once dominated, for ten points, what West African country ruled by Britain as the Gold Coast colony?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Ghana</u></b> (prompt on \"Gold Coast\" before mentioned\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man's illegitimate son Don John pacified a rebellion of former Muslims in Alpujarras [[al-poo-HAH-rahs]] and led a fleet which included a young Miguel De Cervantes [[sehr-VAHN-tehs]]. This Holy Roman Emperor outlawed Martin Luther's teachings in the Diet of Worms [[VURMS]], and he deployed <em>conquistadores</em> like Hern\u00e1n Cort\u00e9s to the New World. For ten points, name this Habsburg Emperor of Spain and Austria, the father of Phillip II.", "answer": "<b><u>Charles V</u></b>, Holy Roman Emperor (accept <b><u>Carlos V</u></b>; or <b><u>Karl V</u></b>; accept <b><u>Charles I of</u></b> <b><u>Spain</u></b>; or <b><u>Carlos I de Espa\u00f1a</u></b>; or <b><u>Charles II of Burgundy</u></b>; or <b><u>Charles II de Bourgogne</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During the investigation of this event, which had many indirect links to the Elohim [[EH-loh-heem]] City compound, Michael Brescia [[BREH-shah]] was briefly detained on suspicion of being the so-called \"John Doe 2.\" Charles Porter took an iconic photograph of the aftermath of this event. The Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building was targeted in this event, for which Terry Nichols was sentenced to life in prison. For ten points, Timothy McVeigh was executed as the main perpetrator of what April 1995 act of right-wing terrorism?", "answer": "<b><u>Oklahoma City Bombing</u></b> (accept similar answers for \u201cBombing\u201d such as \u201cAttack\u201d; accept answers that indicate the attack on the Alfred P. <b><u>Murrah</u></b> Federal <b><u>Building</u> </b>before it is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Despite Social Democrat attempts at moderating this government, radicals such as Alfred Hugenberg [[HYOO-gen-berg]], Ernst Thalmann's Red Front, and the Brownshirts played a key role in bringing it down. In 1932, this government's presidential election saw a World War One general, Paul von Hindenburg, claim victory. This government fell after its parliament burned down, leading to the Reichstag Fire Decree. For ten points, name this democratic German government.", "answer": "<b><u>Weimar</u></b> Republic (or <b><u>Weimar</u></b>er Republik; accept <b><u>German Republic</u></b> or <b><u>Deutsche Republik</u></b> before \"German\" is mentioned; accept \"Reich\" in place of \"Republic\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "John Hyrcanus [[heer-KAH-nooss]] subjugated and converted Itureans [[\"eye\"-TOO-ree-ans]] to this faith after a prolonged campaign. Two scholars of this faith who convinced the Himyarite [[HIM-yah-rite]] king Abu Karib to lift his siege of Yathrib later facilitated his conversion to this faith. The kingdom of Judah's fall to Nebuchadnezzar's [[NEH-boo-kahd-ZEH-zars]] forces led to a period experienced by this faith's adherents known as the Babylonian Captivity. For ten points, name this dominant faith of the Israelites.", "answer": "<b><u>Judaism</u></b> (accept <b><u>Jew</u></b>ish Faith; or <b><u>Jew</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "A subspecies of this animal named for the London Underground is thought to have caused a human encephalitis [[en-seh-fah-LAI-tiss]] outbreak in New York City. A \"wooden wonder\" manufactured by de Havilland and named for this animal was a high-speed light bomber used in World War Two. A Central American coastal kingdom that shares its name with this animal became a British protectorate before being annexed by Nicaragua. A major vector for historical and modern diseases like Yellow Fever and Malaria is, for ten points, what blood-sucking insect?", "answer": "<b><u>Mosquito</u></b>es (accept <em><b><u>Culicidae</u></b></em>; accept London Underground <b><u>Mosquito</u></b>es; accept <b><u>Mosquito</u></b> Coast)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Germany long resisted the implementation of this policy until the SPD made it the key point of coalition negotiations in 2013. A 1994 article by Alan Kreuger and David Card found that differences in this policy between New Jersey and Pennsylvania did not affect employment rates. This policy was first implemented in the U.S. by the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 and was last changed in 2007 at the federal level when it was set at $7.25. For ten points, name this lowest legally allowed rate for hourly labor compensation.", "answer": "<b><u>Minimum wage</u></b> (prompt on descriptive answers)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "The <em>M\u00fcnzmeister</em> [[MOONTS-my-stuh]] were heads of one of these facilities first established in the Carolingian [[kay-roh-LIN-jee-an]] Empire, usually coming from the burgher class. In ancient Rome, these institutions evolved from the Temples of Juno Moneta. The oldest of these buildings was likely in Lydia [[LID-ee-ah]] and produced items made from electrum. The Fugio Cent was made by the United States' first example of these institutions. Often incorporating images of rulers and presidents, for ten points, what institutions produce coins?", "answer": "<b><u>Mint</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Moneyer</u></b>s; prompt on \"banks\"; prompt on descriptive answers involving making money)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Wadai Sultanate annexed a kingdom southeast of this body of water which was ruled by \"Mbang\" kings and was called Bagirmi. Ibn Furtu chronicled the military exploits of a <em>Mai</em> of an empire near this body of water named Idris Alooma. This lake shares its name with a country which with Libya fought the Toyota War over the Aouzu Strip. This lake in the Sahel has shrunk by 95% since 1960. For ten points, identify this lake that names a country governed from N\u2019Djamena [[uhn-jah-MAY-nuh]].", "answer": "Lake <b><u>Chad</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This modern country was the heartland of the medieval Mutapa Empire. This country's predecessor state was governed briefly by Bishop Muzorewa [[moo-zoh-REH-wah]] following the Lancaster House Agreement. A \"Bush War\" in this country ended with the rise of the ZANU-PF and its leader Robert Mugabe. Mugabe's thirty-year presidency occurred in, for ten points, what southeast African country that succeeded Rhodesia?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Zimbabwe</u></b> (accept Republic of <b><u>Rhodesia</u></b> or Southern <b><u>Rhodesia</u></b> until mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Supported by Guadalupe Victoria, this figure rose in rebellion against Emperor Augustin I [[ow-goo-STEEN the first]] in the Casa Mata Plan Revolution. This perpetrator of the Goliad Massacre gave a full military burial to his leg after it was hit by cannon fire during the Pastry War. This man captured the former mission-turned-fort of the Alamo during the War of Texan Independence. For ten points, name this Mexican general and president who resisted an 1840s invasion of his nation by the Polk administration.", "answer": "Antonio L\u00f3pez de <b><u>Santa Anna</u></b> (accept Antonio de Padua Mar\u00eda Severino L\u00f3pez de <b><u>Santa Anna</u></b> y P\u00e9rez de Lebr\u00f3n)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man bucked the trends of post-Civil War historiography in his book <em>Black</em> <em>Reconstruction in America</em>. This thinker, who publicly debated white supremacist Lothrop Stoddard, was the founding editor of the magazine <em>The Crisis</em>. This man believed that full civil rights would be accomplished through the efforts of a group he dubbed the \"Talented Tenth.\" For ten points, name this American-Ghanaian sociologist who wrote <em>The Souls of</em> <em>Black Folk</em>.", "answer": "W. E. B. <b><u>Du Bois</u></b> [[doo-BOYS]] (or William Edward Burghardt <b><u>Du Bois</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Union control was solidified in this U.S. state after Don Carlos Buell's strategic victory at the Battle of Perryville. According to President Lincoln, losing this state was \"nearly the same as to lose the whole game.\" This state's city of Paducah was raided in 1864 by Confederate general Nathan Bedford Forrest. Though neither man represented this state, it was the birthplace of both Jefferson Davis and Abraham Lincoln. For ten points, name this border state during the U.S. Civil War.", "answer": "<b><u>Kentucky</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The ancient city of Zadracarta sat on this body of water and was the seat of power of Hyrcania. This body of water marked the western extent of the Chinese Empire during the Tang Dynasty, and it was primarily explored by Fedor Soimonov [[SOY-mon-off]] during the reign of Peter the Great. The city of Derbent, which lies on this body of water, was handed over in the Treaty of Gulistan from Persia to Russia. For ten points, name this largest inland body of water, named for an ancient Caucasian tribe.", "answer": "<b><u>Caspian</u></b> Sea (accept <b><u>Mazandaran</u></b> Sea; or <b><u>Hyrcania</u></b> Sea; or <b><u>Khazar</u></b> Sea; accept <b><u>Kaspiyskoye</u></b> more; accept <b><u>Hazar</u></b> denizi)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The oldest-known evidence of this kind of event was found on a three thousand-year old Japanese skeleton discovered in 2021. A number of these incidents occurred on the Jersey Shore in 1916, and, after being torpedoed by the Japanese in 1945, the survivors of the USS <em>Indianapolis</em> dealt with hundreds of these incidents while waiting for rescue. For ten points, name these historically-feared events in which a large cartilaginous [[kar-tih-LAH-jih-nus]] fish injures or kills a human.", "answer": "<b><u>Shark attack</u></b> (or <b><u>Shark bite</u></b>; accept descriptive answers involving humans being attacked and/or injured by <b><u>shark</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This author created Sylvia Gellburg, a Jewish woman who falls victim to psychosomatic paralysis after reading an article about <em>Kristallnacht</em>. The outing of this writer's Communist sympathies by his former friend Elia Kazan to the House Un-American Activities Committee was parodied in his play, <em>A View from the Bridge</em>. Joe Keller knowingly ships defective aircraft parts during the Second World War in this author's play <em>All My Sons</em>.  The author of <em>The Crucible</em> was, for ten points, which mid-20th century playwright?", "answer": "Arthur <b><u>Miller</u></b> (or Arthur Asher <b><u>Miller</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "\"Dynamic cubist\" Jacob Lawrence painted a 60-panel series about this event, which is the subject of Isabel Wilkerson's <em>The Warmth of Other Suns</em>. Chester Burnett and Muddy Waters moved to Chicago during this event, which presaged the Harlem Renaissance. For ten points, name this major demographic shift in the mid-twentieth century United States, in which millions of African Americans moved out of the South.", "answer": "Great <b><u>Migration</u></b> (accept Great Northward <b><u>Migration</u></b>; or Black <b><u>Migration</u></b>; accept <em><b><u>Migration</u></b> Series</em>; or <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Migration</u></b> of the Negro</em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In this election year, volunteers were encouraged to \u201cgo clean for Gene\u201d while</u></b> <b><u>supporting Eugene McCarthy in the New Hampshire primary. Curtis LeMay earned</u></b> <b><u>controversy for suggesting the use of (+)</u> nuclear weapons in this year as the vice-presidential nominee for George Wallace\u2019s third-party run. Richard Daley was accused of using \u201cGestapo (*) </b>Tactics\u201d at this year\u2019s DNC in Chicago, which nominated Hubert Humphrey. For ten points, name this election year when Richard Nixon won his first term in office.", "answer": "<b><u>1968</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Several powers in this conflict were criticized in the pamphlet</u> </b><em><b><u>The Conduct of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>the Allies</u></b></em><b><u>. A 70-day siege of Tournai [[toor-NAY]] occurred during this conflict, in</u></b> <b><u>which one side lost over 10,000 men in a victory over the Duke of Villars. A monopoly</u></b> <b><u>over the (+)</u> slave trade was given to England in the treaty ending this conflict. A battle in this war led to a number of poems written to celebrate the Duke of (*) </b>Marlborough. For ten points, name this Europe-wide conflict in which the Battle of Blenheim [[BLEN-em]] was fought.", "answer": "War of the <b><u>Spanish Succession</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Historian Walter LaFeber [[lah-FEE-ber]] wrote that U.S. intervention in this</u></b> <b><u>overseas conflict marked \u201cthe origins of modern presidential powers.\u201d Five thousand</u></b> <b><u>troops from the U.S. were sent by President McKinley to quell this rebellion</u></b> <b><u>sometimes called the (+)</u> Y\u00ech\u00e9tu\u00e1n [[YEE-HEH-TWAHN]] Movement. This armed conflict arose from increasing tensions between foreign missionaries and (*) </b>Chinese rebels. For ten points, name this late 19th-century Chinese rebellion led by the Righteous and Harmonious Fists.", "answer": "<b><u>Boxer</u></b> Rebellion (or <b><u>Boxer</u></b> Uprising; accept <b><u>Y\u00ech\u00e9tu\u00e1n</u></b> Movement or <b><u>Y\u00ech\u00e9tu\u00e1n</u> </b>y\u00f9nd\u00f2ng before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An Aristophanes [[ah-reh-STOH-fah-nees]] play titled for this occupation</u></b> <b><u>included a competition of who can be more shameless between a sausage seller and</u></b> <b><u>an analogue of the politician Creon. Arcite [[ahr-SEE-teh]] and Palamon are (+)</u> two soldiers imprisoned in a tower by Theseus and fall in love with his sister-in-law Emelye [[\"Emily\"]] in a \"Tale\" (*) </b>named for this profession. In one story, Gawain battles a \"Green\" one of these people. For ten points, name this medieval chivalric class of warriors.", "answer": "<b><u>Knight</u></b>s (accept <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Knight</u></b>s</em>; accept <b><u>Knight</u></b>'s Tale; accept <b><u>Hippeis</u></b>; prompt on \"Cavalry\" or \"Horsemen\")", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>While proconsul of Cilicia [[sih-LIH-shuh]], this man marched two battered</u></b> <b><u>legions to relieve the siege of fellow governor Cassius from a Parthian siege at</u></b> <b><u>Antioch. Publius Clodius Pulcher [[POOL-care]] directly targeted this politician by</u></b> <b><u>passing a law to exile any public official who (+)</u> executed a Roman citizen without trial. This man, who put down the Cataline Conspiracy, later refused to join the (*) </b>First Triumvirate. For ten points, name this Roman orator of the 1st century B.C.", "answer": "Marcus Tullius <b><u>Cicero</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A bank connected to this man run by Roberto Calvi faced controversy after it</u></b> <b><u>funneled money to both sides of the Nicaraguan Civil War. This figure narrowly</u></b> <b><u>escaped the Nazi Black Sunday roundup of youth after the Warsaw (+)</u> Ghetto uprising, hiding in his uncle\u2019s basement in Krakow. Grey Wolves member Mehmet Ali Agca [[AHD-juh]] fired and injured this (*) </b>holy figure in St. Peter\u2019s Square. For ten points, name this Polish Pope who was succeeded by Benedict XVI [[the sixteenth]].", "answer": "Pope <b><u>John Paul II</u></b> (or <b><u>Ioannes Paulus II</u></b>; accept Karol J\u00f3zef <b><u>Wojty\u0142a</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man was born in the Wallowa [[wall-OW-ah]] Valley with a name</u></b> <b><u>meaning \"Thunder Rolling Down the Mountain.\" This man\u2019s heart was \u201csick and sad\u201d</u></b> <b><u>in 1877 after he failed to escape into (+)</u> Canada and was forced to surrender to U.S. soldiers led by Nelson Miles. This man was a leader of a tribe that is often known by a two-word (*) </b>French phrase meaning \u201cpierced nose.\u201d For ten points, name this Nez Perc\u00e9 [[NEZ \"PURSE\"]] chief who vowed \u201cI will fight no more forever.\u201d", "answer": "Chief <b><u>Joseph</u></b> (or <b><u>In-mut-too-yah-lat-lat</u></b>; or <b><u>Hin-mah-too-yah-lat-kekt</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Because of this man\u2019s system of natural philosophy, Gisbert Voetius [[GIZ-</u><u>behrt VEE-tee-ooss]] persuaded the University of Utrecht [[YOO-trekt]] to condemn</u></b> <b><u>this man, who retaliated with the publication of</u> </b><em><b><u>Comments on a Certain Broadsheet</u></b></em><b><u>.</u></b> <b><u>Using the (+)</u> \u201cWax Example,\u201d this man theorized that things are perceived through our intellect, and he believed deductive reasoning proved God\u2019s (*) </b>existence. This man developed a system to plot points on a namesake plane. For ten points, name this French mathematician and philosopher whose views are best exemplified by his quote, \u201cI think therefore I am.\u201d", "answer": "Ren\u00e9 <b><u>Descartes</u></b> [[deh-KAHRT]] (or Renatus <b><u>Cartesius</u></b>; prompt on \"Cartesian\")", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>The earliest example of these objects were found in Oregon's Fort Rock Cave.</u></b> <b><u>A set of these objects belonging to \u00d6tzi [[UHT-zee]] the Ice Man had a bearskin base</u></b> <b><u>and deerskin side panels. (+)</u> Caligula's nickname derived from a pair of \"little\" examples of these objects, an example of which, the (*) </b>moccasin, was worn by Native Americans. Alpargatas and clogs are historical examples of, for ten points, what articles of clothing?", "answer": "<b><u>shoe</u></b>s (accept <b><u>boot</u></b>s; or <b><u>sandal</u></b>s; or <b><u>footwear</u></b>; or specific examples like <b><u>Moccasin</u></b>s before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}], "bonuses": []}